Krishnapriya Vishnubhotla

✓ vkpriya@cs.toronto.edu • ♦ https://priya22.github.io/

I graduated in June 2024 with a PhD in Computer Science from the University of Toronto, where I was part of the Computational Linguistics group, supervised by **Graeme Hirst** and **Frank Rudzicz**. My PhD projects focused on modelling variation in language use as a function of speaker identity, a research area that falls in the intersection of natural language processing, sociolinguistics, and psycholinguistics. I am interested in leveraging large text datasets to better understand how facets of individual identity and communicative goals affect the ways in which information is conveyed via language, more broadly in the applications of NLP technologies in the social sciences and humanities.

Education

University of Toronto Toronto

PhD in Computer Science, Computational Linguistics Group, GPA: 3.97/4.0 2019–2024

University of Toronto

Moster of Science in Computer Science Thesis antica, CDA 40/40

2017, 2010

Master of Science in Computer Science, Thesis option, GPA: 4.0/4.0

2017–2019

National Institute of Technology Karnataka-Surathkal

B. Tech Computer Science and Engineering , CGPA 8.93/10

Mangalore, India
2013–2017

Experience

National Research Council (NRC) Canada

Toronto

Research Intern June 2023 – Jan 2024

Formulated metrics to characterize emotional expression and variation among different demographic groups using social media utterances, and their connection to various mental health conditions.

Al4Good Lab Toronto

Teaching Assistant April 2022 – June 2022

The Al4Good Lab is a 7-week introductory machine learning program for under-represented groups in the field. As a TA, I designed and ran daily tutorial sessions on ML theory, programming, and mentored teams on an applied NLP project on style transfer.

Georgian Partners Toronto

Research Intern May 2020 – Dec 2020

Worked on developing unsupervised clustering models of text embeddings for internal company applications.

Samsung Al Research Center

Research Intern May 2019 – Sep 2019

Worked on multi-modal representation learning and semi-supervised methods of text and video alignment. I was a part of the winning submission for the Samsung Retail Robot Challenge, for which we built an interactive clip retrieval system for customer support videos.

Myntra Designs Inc.

Bangalore, India

Software Engineering Intern

May 2016 – July 2016

Worked on backend and frontend development of web interfaces for customer service chatbots.

IIT-Bombay Mumbai, India

Summer Research Intern May 2015 – July 2015

Worked on characterizing Nash equilibrium of quasi-zero-sum games.

Research Themes

o Comparing Character Portrayal in Human and Machine Story Generations (Sep 2023-Jan 2024))

Created the GPT-WritingPrompts dataset, which pairs short stories written by Reddit users in response to prompts with comparable generations from GPT-3.5. Quantified and compared biases in character portrayal when grouped by the narrative voice and the gender of the main protagonist of the story.

Characterizing Emotional Expression and Variation in Social Media Utterances (Oct 2021-Mar 2024)

Developed computational measures of Emotional Dynamics and Emotion Granularity from textual utterances, metrics used in the affective sciences as markers of physical and emotional well-being. Demonstrated their effectiveness as markers of mental health for multiple Mental Health Conditions. Work done in collaboration with members of the Affective Science Lab, University of North Carolina Chapel Hill.

Quotation Attribution and Character Voice in Literary Texts (Sept 2019-Dec 2023)

Created the Project Dialogism Novel Corpus (PDNC), a large dataset of characters and their quotations in full-length literary novels. Designed and evaluated neural models that can accurately attribute quotations to their speakers. Modelled effects of speaker and author identity on stylistic and emotional features of utterances.

A Dataset of Semantic Textual Relatedness (March 2020-Jan 2021)

Created a dataset of sentence pairs annotated for semantic relatedness using Best–Worst Scaling. Explored the contribution of various linguistic features to semantic relatedness, and evaluated state-of-the-art sentence representation models on the dataset.

Disentangling Content and Style in Texts (Sept 2019-Jan 2020)

Evaluated autoencoder variants that learn disentangled representations of content and style on a highly-structured Natural Language Generation dataset. Our findings highlight the data requirements, effectiveness, and limitations of current learning methods.

Publications

Working Papers

- Huang, X.Y., Vishnubhotla, K. and Rudzicz, F., 2024. The GPT-WritingPrompts Dataset: A Comparative Analysis
 of Character Portrayal in Short Stories. arXiv preprint arXiv:2406.16767. Under review
- Vishnubhotla, K., Teodorescu, D., Feldman, M.J., Lindquist, K.A. and Mohammad, S.M., 2024. Emotion Granularity from Text: An Aggregate-Level Indicator of Mental Health. arXiv preprint arXiv:2403.02281. *Under review*

Refereed Publications

- Vishnubhotla, K., Hammond, A., Hirst, G., and Mohammad, S.M., 2024. The Emotion Dynamics of Literary Novels. In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2024)
- Ousidhoum, N., Muhammad, S.H., Abdalla, M., et al., 2024. SemRel2024: A Collection of Semantic Textual Relatedness Datasets for 14 Languages. In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2024).
- Vishnubhotla, K., Rudzicz, F., Hirst, G., and Hammond, A., 2023. Improving Quotation Attribution in Literary Novels. In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 2: Short Papers) (ACL 2023)
- Abdalla M., <u>Vishnubhotla, K.</u> and Mohammad, S.M., 2023. What Makes Sentences Semantically Related: A
 Textual Relatedness Dataset and Empirical Study. In *Proceedings of the 17th Conference of the European Chapter*of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EMNLP 2023)
- Vishnubhotla, K., Hammond, A. and Hirst, G., 2022. The Project Dialogism Novel Corpus: A Dataset for Quotation Attribution in Literary Texts. In *Proceedings of the 13th Language Resources and Evaluation Conference (LREC 2022)*
- Vishnubhotla, K. and Mohammad, S.M., 2022. Tweet Emotion Dynamics: Emotion Word Usage in Tweets from US and Canada. In Proceedings of the 13th Language Resources and Evaluation Conference (LREC 2022)
- Vishnubhotla, K., Hirst, G. and Rudzicz, F., 2021. An Evaluation of Disentangled Representation Learning for Texts. In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2021)
- Vishnubhotla, K., Hammond, A. and Hirst, G., 2019. Are Fictional Voices Distinguishable? Classifying Character Voices in Modern Drama. In Proceedings of the 3rd Joint SIGHUM Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, Humanities and Literature (LaTeCH-CLfL 2019)
- Budhkar, A., Vishnubhotla, K., Hossain, S. and Rudzicz, F., 2019. Generative Adversarial Networks for Text Using Word2vec Intermediaries. In Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Representation Learning for NLP (RepL4NLP-2019)

Teaching Experience

- o Co-Instructor: Introductory Computation and Data Science for the Life and Physical Sciences, (Winter 2024)
- Lead TA: Introductory Computation and Data Science for the Social Sciences, Life and Physical Sciences, and Literature, (Winter 2023, Fall 2023)
- Teaching Assistant: Natural Language Computing, Introduction To Computer Programming, Introduction to Computer Science, Programming on the Web. (2017 to 2022, various semesters.)

Academic Service

- O Research Mentorship: Xi Yu Huang, May-December 2023.
- I have served as a reviewer for:
 - o ACL Rolling Review: 2024, 2023, 2022
 - o *ACL Conferences (ACL, NAACL, EMNLP): 2022, 2021, 2020, 2019, 2018
- O Volunteer mentor for the Graduate Application Assistance Program, 2021.
- O Triager for the DCS Admissions Program, 2021 and 2020.
- o Maintained the official webpage of the Computational Linguistics group, University of Toronto, from 2018-2020.

Awards

- O Vector Research Grant, Vector Institute, Toronto (2019–2024)
- o SGS and DCS Conference Grants, University of Toronto (2021, 2023)
- o Ministry of Human Resources and Development India Undergraduate Scholarship (2013-2017)

Technical skills

- O Deep Learning Frameworks: PyTorch, TensorFlow
- o Programming Languages: C, C++, Javascript, Python, R

Relevant Courses

- o (Advanced) Computational Linguistics o Natural Language Computing o Introduction to Machine Learning
- O Learning Discrete Latent Structure O Algorithms for Private Data Analysis O Topics in Computational Social Science
- Computational Models of Semantic Change